JIM: Previously on Gotham...
DWIGHT: It's
you. It's really you.
(LAUGHING MANIACALLY)
Oh, no. Somebody help!
Penguin. He
killed the librarian.
I don't wanna kill him.
I want to destroy him!
GUS: And you promised them
Jerome. They want to see his face!
DWIGHT: Behold, the prophet.
ALL: We are Jerome!
You get the message? We
don't work for you no more.
COBBLEPOT: I will gut you!
- Then Nygma dies.
- They have Ed.
JEROME: When I was
last, you know, uh, alive,
I was about to kill Bruce Wayne.
Well, where is my face?
(TELEPHONE RINGING)
- What?
- ED: Oswald.
- Where are you?
- Cane Chemicals.
Oswald, hurry, please...
JEROME: Tonight,
Gotham, there are no rules.
And when morning comes...
You, too, shall be reborn.
(LAUGHING MANIACALLY)
JIM: He's at the power
plant across the river.
- (MEN SHOUTING)
- (MAN LAUGHS MANIACALLY)
Get those freaks in the cages.
We need to find Jerome.
Hey! Watch him!
(GRUNTS)
What about you? Do you
know where Jerome is?
- Where is he?
- Where is he? Look around.
He's everywhere!
MAN: Incoming! Get up.
Tonight,
Gotham is awakened!
(LAUGHING MANIACALLY)
(THEME MUSIC PLAYING)
(HUFFING) Remember,
Ed's safety is all that matters.
Whoever took him will pay,
but only once Ed is back.
Ed?
Edward?
(PANTING)
Are you all right?
Tell me you're all right.
- I'm fine, Oswald.
- (LAUGHS)
Of course you are.
Where are they?
Who dared to think they
could lay their hands on you?
I'm alone.
(CHUCKLES) You escaped?
Yeah, you did, didn't
you? You rascal!
- Did you bring anyone else?
- What? Why? No...
Just wondering if I was
gonna have to reload.
- I don't understand.
- I know.
That's been half the fun.
I'm sorry, I...
What is happening? I...
You weren't kidnapped?
Not unless you count
kidnapping yourself.
Recognize it?
But, why should you? I doubt
you did the deed yourself.
That car belonged to Isabella.
Ed. Whatever you've heard...
(GRUNTS)
I know it was you, Oswald.
Isabella was my everything,
and you took her from me.
And now, I've taken
everything from you.
Well, almost everything.
You still have your life
but that ends tonight!
MAN: (ON SPEAKER) Attention,
all residents. Stay off the streets...
A curfew is in effect for
Gotham City until further notice.
Seems like judgment came to
Gotham earlier than expected.
If the situation worsens,
we may be forced to step in.
(EXPLOSIONS IN THE DISTANCE)
The city will bend
long before it breaks.
Give the GCPD a chance.
Your faith in him is touching.
And possibly dangerous.
(INDISTINCT SHOUTING, LAUGHTER)
We're getting reports of a
riot growing on the west side,
as well as widespread
looting uptown.
Mobs of cult members
have taken over Anders Park,
Gotham Cathedral... The zoo?
All right. Concentrate
units on the west side.
Make sure they're issued riot
gear. Any word on Jerome Valeska?
Nothing yet.
Let me know as
soon as he's spotted.
Right. Got it.
Lights aren't coming back
tonight. Tomorrow, if we're lucky.
This thing just keeps getting
bigger. It's not just the cult anymore.
Ordinary citizens are
taking Jerome's cue.
- (TELEPHONE RINGING)
- Meanwhile Cobblepot's MIA.
You call down to City Hall,
and literally no one's in charge.
Although that might
actually be good news.
We need to find
Jerome. He's the symbol.
If we can take him out, maybe we
can limit this to a single bad night.
Now how the hell are we
supposed to find him out there?
- The city's one giant dumpster fire.
- (TELEPHONE CONTINUES RINGING)
Jerome said he wanted to
plunge the city into darkness
so people could do
what they want, right?
He's not one to miss out on
the fun. So, what does he want?
A puppy? How the hell should
I know? I didn't talk to him.
- (TELEPHONE CONTINUES RINGING)
- No. But Lee did.
Yes?
Listen, my father
appeared to me. (GRUNTS)
I saw him.
No.
You saw a man that
I met in Indian Hill.
Does killer impersonations.
You see, Oswald,
how do I put this?
Ghosts aren't real.
But my father's remains?
You stole them from his grave?
Yep. Don't worry.
He's at peace now.
I gently placed his remains inside a
dumpster behind a Chinese restaurant.
You were angry. I
understand. I even forgive you.
But, but killing
me is not the way.
So, you admit
you killed Isabella.
- Fine. Is that what you want?
- Yes!
I confess, I had her killed.
But guess what?
You should thank me.
Because we both know what
would have happened if I hadn't.
Yes!
I could have lived a life
with the woman I loved.
I could've been happy.
No, Ed. You would
have killed her.
Just like you did the other
one. You couldn't have helped it.
And afterward, you
would have hated yourself.
Well,
we'll never know, will we?
I did it for love.
What?
I did it because I love you.
- You should know that.
- Shut up!
Love is about sacrifice.
It's about putting someone else's
needs and happiness before your own.
- Ed, please.
- The truth is, Oswald,
you would sacrifice anyone
to save your own neck.
Even me. Now.
If you'll look above us,
you'll see a cauldron
of highly corrosive acid
which is currently being
held in place by this chain.
When the ice melts,
the chain comes loose,
the vat of acid tips.
You get the idea.
- (VALVE SQUEAKS)
- (GAS HISSING)
Ed. Please, please,
I can change.
Say you're right,
say you're right.
The fact that I love you
proves that I can change.
Just give me a chance.
You know as well as I
that a man facing death
will say anything to save his
skin. And you won't change.
Because you can't.
I was going to have
you say hello to Isabella,
- but...
- (CHOKING)
I think you are going
to a very different place.
- (GASPS)
- Goodbye, Oswald.
Ed!
Ed! Ed!
Okay, I think that's
about all I can do.
Thanks.
How's triage going?
A lot of overflow
from Gotham General.
What do you want?
When Jerome woke
up, did he say anything?
Said he wanted his face back.
No. I mean, anything that might
indicate where he was going?
- What he was planning?
- We were just playing catch up.
You know, about coming
back to life. The cult.
He asked if you and
I were still together.
I mentioned you killed my
husband on our wedding night.
And he thought
that was hilarious
so that's something the two of you
can bond over when you find him.
He didn't tell me his plan.
He talked about
Galavan, the night he died.
And then he mentioned...
- What?
- Bruce.
He said the last
thing he remembers
is that he was gonna
kill Bruce Wayne.
Call Alfred. Tell
him I'm on my way.
- I'll light these candles.
- Good lad.
I'll go downstairs to see if there's
any life left in that old generator.
(TELEPHONE RINGING)
Who's calling at this hour?
Alfred?
(GRUNTING)
(JEROME LAUGHING MOCKINGLY)
Ooh!
My, my.
Look how big you've gotten.
(LAUGHS)
- (MEN CHATTERING)
- (GLASS SHATTERING)
Are you okay?
I'll be fine, Master
Bruce. I'll be fine.
JEROME: Nice place
you got here. You rent?
- What do you want?
- (GLASS SHATTERING)
Attitude.
Teenagers, am I right?
Oh, I remember those days.
So many exciting new
emotions floating through you.
Wanting to kill
everyone you saw.
Oh...
You. Give me.
You know, I will never
understand rich people's tastes.
It's worthless. My father
found it at a flea market.
- I keep it for sentimental reasons.
- Nice try.
Oh, it's got some heft to it.
Expensive, I'm guessing.
It'd be such a shame if I...
No! Don't...
JEROME: Oh...
Tougher than I figured. Anyway.
Oh, bloody hell.
- I asked you what you want.
- Right. Sorry.
The old noodle's still a
little al dente post thaw.
The reason I'm here
is I'm gonna kill you.
- Why?
- Well,
just last thing I
remember wanting to do.
It's been nagging at
me since I woke up.
The idea of slitting that
pretty, pink throat of yours.
Figure that'll clear the
decks. What do you think?
- Don't you...
- (GUN COCKS)
I remember that night.
When you took over the benefit.
You were quite the showman.
Thank you. Always
nice being appreciated.
And you're just
going to kill me here.
It's kind of disappointing.
Ah, what do you mean?
After all the buildup,
you coming back to life,
turning off the
lights in Gotham,
killing me here just
doesn't show a lot of...
Flair? Style? Panache? Hmm?
Go on, boy, spit
it out. I can take it.
- I'm Bruce Wayne.
- I'm aware.
I am the ruling elite.
My company is the machine that
keeps the cogs of Gotham running.
Wow.
Killing me should
mean something.
And you're telling me
no one's going to see it?
You're saying I
need an audience?
Oh...
Look, I know you're just trying
to buy time so you can escape.
But your point is still valid.
Saddle up, boys. We're
taking this show on the road.
And I know just
the spot. Come on.
Eh-eh-eh.
Not you, old chap.
The prince of Gotham
deserves a public death.
His butler? Not
so much. Kill him.
- No!
- Bruce!
This is what you've
been training for.
You're gonna be
all right on your own.
I will see you again.
You carry on, son, you carry on.
Strangely intimate.
Come on. Mmm.
Try not to get any
blood on the couch.
I might come back for that.
COBBLEPOT: (GASPING) Help!
Somebody help me! Help!
(SCREAMING)
(ACID SIZZLING)
- Help!
- MAN: Hello?
(GASPING) Over here!
Oh! (LAUGHS)
Oh, thank God.
There's not much time!
Cut me loose! Hurry!
- What's that car doing here?
- Does it matter? Cut me loose.
- Hey, you, you look familiar.
- Oh, yes.
I happen to be the
Mayor of Gotham.
So, free me.
And I promise there will
be a handsome reward.
Holy... It really is you. The
Mayor of Gotham, in the flesh.
Yes! Now stop standing
there and get me out of here!
I don't... I don't know.
- What did you do?
- What?
Oh, I'm gonna die here
listening to this moron.
- Just cut the ropes!
- Okay, okay, okay.
(GASPING) Oh, God.
- Hurry!
- Yeah.
(COBBLEPOT CONTINUES GASPING)
(GLASS SHATTERING)
MAN: Whoopsie! (LAUGHS)
Fine, come on then.
What are you waiting for?
MAN 1: You in a
rush to die, old man?
Who's gonna kill him?
Who's gonna do him?
- MAN 2: I'll do him.
- What? What, you three?
You three left here to take
out the rubbish, were ya?
You, Mr. Machine gun
with the suits of armor,
I want you to shoot
me in the grill, are ya?
How about you with
the crowbar by the sofa?
Gonna cave in my skull? And
how about you, Mr. Machete?
Oh, come on in,
Sunshine, don't be shy.
Your mama wasn't. Chop, chop.
- Who're you talking to, old man?
- JIM: Me.
(GROANS)
(GRUNTING)
(GROANING)
- Where's Bruce?
- That lunatic Jerome took him.
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
(GUNFIRE NEARBY)
(CARNIVAL MUSIC PLAYING)
(EXHALES)
(MAN GASPS)
- (MEN LAUGHING)
- WOMAN: No, please. No.
- (WOMAN GROANING)
- (MEN CONTINUE LAUGHING)
(GRUNTS)
(INDISTINCT SHOUTING)
Get him. Squash her.
(MAN GRUNTING)
Get the old lady. Come on.
The fat guy. Put
your back into it.
Oh.
(JEROME CHUCKLES)
Well, we're off to a good start.
What do you say, Bruce?
Wanna have some fun
before the main event?
Bullock's pulling
messages from the tip line.
You said Bruce was
able to convince Jerome
to kill him in front
of an audience?
Yeah, he's trying to buy
himself some more time.
I would be proud if I
wasn't so bloody terrified.
City's given way
to Bedlam again.
Get down. Get in. Oh, shut up.
Jerome's acolytes have
occupied places all over town, so
finding an audience
won't be the issue.
- The question is where.
- BULLOCK: We got him.
They're in Anders
Park, the cathedral,
the zoo, they've taken over
the Hillside Conservatory,
the Courthouse and
The Boardwalk Circus.
Jerome was raised in a circus.
Have a Strike Force and all
available units meet us there.
I'll put out the call
on the way. Let's roll.
(EXCITED CHATTER)
Gotta be honest, Bruce,
you don't make the
world's funniest clown.
But...
MAN: Ooh!
We can fix that.
(GROANING)
(JEROME EXHALES)
- (MAN GRUNTING)
- (FLESH SQUELCHING)
Ah, shut up, you big baby.
Let's turn that
frown upside down.
Gabe!
We need have to find
Ed Nygma and kill him!
- (WHIP CRACKS)
- Gabe, where... (CHOKING)
Your monkeys cleared out.
Now what's that you
were saying about Nygma?
Looks like we're not the
only ones trying to kill that guy.
- Now, where is he?
- F...
- I'm sorry, what? Speak up.
- (GASPING)
- What are you doing in my house?
- TABITHA: Whatever we want.
You're finished, Oswald.
Now, where's Nygma?
I don't know.
Think.
- What?
- I said, think!
Oh, I heard you. I'm just
surprised you knew the word.
(LAUGHS) Speaking
of words. Any last ones?
Babs said not to kill
him until we have Nygma.
I don't work for Barbara Kean.
Oh...
Stop pretending that you
are anything but muscle.
Yes, you used to be
someone in Gotham,
but those days are
past! (GROANS)
(TABITHA GRUNTS)
Remember when I put a
knife in your mom's back?
That was awful, wasn't it?
Her crying, bleeding out, you
just holding her as she died.
And you never did
anything about it.
Yet.
Nah. You had your
chance to kill me.
Stop turning us
against each other.
We're taking him with us.
Oh, if you think I am
going anywhere with you...
(GRUNTS)
You realize you have
to carry him now?
Son of a bitch.
(PEOPLE SCREAMING)
- (MAN LAUGHING)
- (WOMAN SCREAMS)
MAN: Oh, I missed.
BRUCE: Is there a
plan for all this madness?
These people don't want a
plan, they want an excuse.
A mother who dreams
of strangling her child.
Husband who
wants to stab his wife.
All they want is
someone to tell them...
"Do it."
Kill them. It doesn't matter.
It doesn't.
Ohh! I love this
game. One please.
MAN: You, sir.
No, no, no. Please.
No, no. No, no.
- You won't get away with it.
- Already did. Now, shush.
Need to concentrate.
(GRUNTS, SPITS)
A few dozen brainwashed maniacs
can't keep the city hostage forever.
Well, duh.
So, what's the point?
The point
is that all these people out
here, looting, robbing, killing...
They're the people who wash
your car, who pour your coffee,
who take out your trash.
And what happened the
moment the lights went out?
They showed their true faces.
They showed how quickly
they want to open up
your rich boy veins and
bathe in your blue blood.
That is the point.
That's not true.
There are good people in Gotham.
(LAUGHING)
Like who?
The sheep who locked their
doors and crawled under their beds?
Face it, kid.
Gotham has no heroes.
- MAN: No. No, no!
- Wait.
Hey.
Foul!
He pushed me, you see that?
You wanna kill someone?
Let's get on with it. Come on.
(YAWNS MOCKINGLY)
You're so boring, Bruce.
- (BELL DINGS)
- (SCREAMING)
No!
Oh. Sorry. You.
(EXHALES)
(GRUNTING)
(GROANS WEAKLY)
Did that hurt?
Not much.
- You try.
- (STAPLER CLICKS)
- Stop!
- (LAUGHS)
- All right.
Enough dilly-dally.
To the main event.
- Where the hell is our backup?
- Still two minutes out.
Most were waylaid by
another riot on the west side.
- Yeah, but we can't wait, mate.
- All right.
So, we go in,
find Bruce, get him to safety.
Then we go after Jerome. Ready?
Not really.
- (PEOPLE SHOUTING)
- MAN: We all know why we're here.
Here comes Jerome!
Everybody! (LAUGHS)
(CROWD CHEERING)
(OVER MEGAPHONE) Hear
ye! Hear ye! Gather round.
The show is about to begin!
(CROWD CHEERING)
(MAN WHOOPING AND LAUGHING)
MAN: Let me hear it.
Come on now. Come on.
(CROWD GASPS)
Shut up!
(LAUGHTER)
Better. (LAUGHS)
Well, I think we can all agree
tonight was a rousing success.
We brought this
miserable city to its knees.
(CROWD CHEERING)
So, how to thank the
best darn cult of fanatics
a messiah like myself
could ever hope for?
I give you...
(FANFARE PLAYS)
Cue!
Oh...
(CROWD CHEERING)
JEROME: I give you the
climax of our festivities.
The billionaire
prince of Gotham,
Bruce Wayne!
Well, so what do you say, Bruce?
Shall we end the night with a
bang? Or better yet, a boom?
(CARNIVAL MUSIC PLAYING)
CROWD: Boom! Boom! Boom! Boom!
Boom! Boom! Boom!
(STRAINING)
All right.
What's next?
Death by 1,000 cuts.
Very poetic. I like it.
So nice.
Nailed it.
All right, folks, this
is very important,
whatever you do, please
definitely try this at home.
Preferably on a family member.
(GRUNTS)
(CROWD LAUGHING)
Yeah.
(CROWD CHEERING)
- You ready, partner?
- Oh, good Lord.
The Strike Force just
arrived. They're coming in.
Detective Gordon!
You're just in time
for the big finish.
JIM: Nobody move!
(GUNFIRE)
(BULLET RICOCHETS)
(LAUGHS)
(GRUNTS)
(GUNFIRE CONTINUES)
Find him. I'll find Jerome.
- (SIREN WAILING)
- (INDISTINCT SHOUTING)
So.
Here we are.
I suppose I underestimated
you, Barbara.
- It's the curse of great beauty.
- How did it go?
You put together what
happened to Ed's librarian,
- turned him against me.
- Honestly, wasn't too hard.
And then together you hatched a
plan to destroy everything I made
- and kill me?
- Pretty much.
And brother, did
you ever take the bait.
(LAUGHS)
Well, I hope you're happy
at the head of the table.
You know, the table is more or
less littered with dead old dudes,
but hey, it's a place
to grow. (CHUCKLES)
And now you've got what you
want, you don't need Ed anymore.
- Mmm. (CHUCKLES)
- (LAUGHS)
My, my. Didn't take you
long to turn on each other.
(SCOFFS)
You know, I think of it as a limited
partnership that needs dissolving.
So, I help you find Ed,
things go better for
me. I don't, you kill me.
That about it?
Yeah.
(BREATHES DEEPLY)
Oh, Bruce. Where are you, boy?
Come on out,
boy. I won't hurt ya.
Bruce, darling.
Oh, Brucey.
You ruined my show, Bruce.
Hiding's just gonna
make things worse.
I didn't come here to hide.
I wanted you to follow me.
You're going to pay
for what you've done.
You're going to call Ed.
Tell him you're
alive. Tell him...
Oh, I don't care. But
find out where he is.
- Why don't you call him?
- Because he's not stupid.
He knows that now
you're no longer
the head of the
underworld or anything else,
we don't need him
anymore. It is our time to rule.
(SCOFFS)
You understand if I
feel compelled to refuse.
Give me five minutes,
he won't refuse.
I'd do it in three.
- Why you gotta do that?
- What?
Cut me down like
that in front of people.
- I'm just saying...
- Would the two of you shut up?
Give up Nygma. And
save your own ass.
Live to love another day. Hey.
Wow.
What's going on? You have
a weird look on your face.
Like, weirder than normal.
You're right.
- I should want him dead.
- "Should?"
Oswald,
you loved him, and
he betrayed you.
Actually, I don't
know that I did.
- Love him. Not really.
- What?
Ed was right.
I thought I loved him
because he saw me as no
one had since my mother.
But I killed Isabelle.
I'm pretty sure her name
is Isabella, but go on.
Because I wouldn't share him.
Ed said love is sacrifice.
I should have been able to
sacrifice my happiness for his.
I couldn't.
But I'm ready now.
(SOBS)
I won't call Ed.
I won't let you hurt him.
So, you'd rather die than give
up the man who tried to kill you?
- (LAUGHS) I would. Isn't that crazy?
- ED: Yes.
It is.
Guess you're not as smart
as you thought you were.
He didn't give you up after all.
You're in this together?
(SIGHS)
But why?
Because I didn't want
to just take what you had.
I wanted to take
what you believed.
I wanted you to die
knowing that you were
incapable of loving another person.
(GASPS) But I can. I
just proved that, right?
Does that mean I
passed? (LAUGHS)
(GASPING)
- Ed?
- I...
Don't know what it means.
(SIGHS)
(GASPS, CHUCKLES)
(EXHALES)
(LAUGHING)
I have to tell you,
this is way more fun
than I was expecting.
We make a good team, you and me.
BRUCE: You killed Alfred.
Is that what this is about?
Yeesh.
Are all rich kids this
close with their butlers?
Oh!
BRUCE: This is about
doing what's right.
You want to be a hero?
Tell you what, buddy, I'll
give you a fighting chance.
Let's do this mano y
mano, my little conquistador.
Come on.
(BOTH GRUNTING)
What kind of hero tackles
someone from behind?
(GRUNTS)
(LAUGHING)
Let it out. That's
it. That's it.
That's it. Let it out.
- Let it out.
- (PANTING)
Do it.
Bruce!
(CHUCKLES)
(GRUNTS SOFTLY)
Do it! (GAGGING)
(SCREAMS)
(GROANING)
(CHUCKLING)
(PEOPLE SHOUTING)
(MAN GRUNTS)
Alfred.
Bruce!
I thought you were dead.
You can't get rid of me
that easily, can you, mate?
Behind you!
Ow!
(GROANING)
(EVIL CHUCKLE)
Word of Jerome's
arrest is spreading quick.
The streets are already quieter.
Soon as the docs reattach
his face, he's off to Arkham.
You wish I would've shot him?
Yeah, he'd probably just
come back from the dead again.
Probably.
At least you get to say you
punched a man's face off.
That's something, right?
- Jim?
- Sorry, what?
Come on. Let me
buy you breakfast.
Well, gotta say,
the clown makeup
was way more terrifying
than the damage
underneath, Master Bruce.
(CHUCKLES)
Did I ever tell you
that I don't like clowns?
Well, in a couple of days...
You'll be back to your
old self. I guarantee it.
You ready to tell
me what happened?
When Jerome took me away,
I thought they were
going to kill you.
Should I tell you
what I thought?
I thought how proud I was of you.
Of the man that you've become.
I almost killed him, Alfred.
Yeah, but you didn't, now, did
you? You controlled your anger.
It wasn't just anger.
After everything
Jerome had done,
after all the pain he caused,
the idea of killing him...
- Felt...
- It felt right.
Yes.
It felt like justice.
There's a very fine
line, Master Bruce,
- between justice and vengeance.
- I know.
But that doesn't
mean there isn't one.
No, it doesn't.
I knew where the line
was tonight, Alfred.
I didn't cross it.
- Well, that's the first rule.
- What do you mean?
Now, I started training you
so you could defend yourself.
Well, we're well
past that, aren't we?
But what's all this training for?
What are you gonna do with it?
- I don't know.
- Nor do I.
But if you keep going,
you're gonna need rules.
Rules you cannot
and you will not break.
Never mind what reason, never
mind what the circumstance.
I will not kill.
Say it again.
Then let's get to work.
KATHRYN: Tonight, was close.
We could have lost
Gotham for good.
Soon, we will act, and
you will be called upon.
I've done a wonderful
job erasing the scars.
- Are you prepared?
- Yes.
But I still don't understand
how I can help save Gotham.
FRANK: Never fear.
You're only part of the plan.
Are you sure about this?
You know what must
happen if he refuses.
I know.
No one refuses the Court.
(KNOCKING ON DOOR)
- Uncle Frank?
- Hello, Jim.
It's been a long time.
Ed, I love you.
I know you believe that now.
So, you need to listen
to me when I tell you,
by doing this, it
will change you.
- I've killed before, Oswald.
- Not like this.
This won't be a crime of
passion or self-preservation.
This will be the cold-blooded
murder of someone you love.
I don't love you.
(GRUNTS)
You need me, Edward Nygma.
Just as I need you.
You cannot have
one without the other.
You killed Isabella.
- The point is...
- That is the point!
You can't talk your
way out of this, Oswald.
I have wanted you to
suffer as I've suffered.
You killed her. So, you die.
When I met you, you
were a nervous, jittery loser.
You were nothing!
I created Edward Nygma!
And I am the only one in the
world who truly sees you as you are.
Who you can still become.
You can't do this.
Ed, are you listening to me?
I'm listening.
Say something.
I loved her, Oswald.
- And you killed her.
- (GUN FIRES)
(EXHALES DEEPLY)
(THEME MUSIC PLAYING)
English -SDH